The following content is provided under a
Creative Commons license. Your support will
help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high -quality educational resources for
free. To make a donation or to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw
.mit .edu. OK. So basic probability ideas
today, because that's a part of the
subject, part of deep learning as we get
there. And it's probably a good topic for
the day before spring break, because lots
of you will have seen, of course, you will
have seen the sample mean, the average of
the data. So we have,
and you'll know about the
expected mean. Let me complete that.
What's the expected mean? So this is the
expectation of the value x, where we get x1
with probability p1, along to xn with
probability pn. So we just want to say,
what's our average output, average outcome?
And we weight it by the probabilities. So
it's p1 x1 plus so on plus pn xn.
So that's the expected value of x.
It involves square. And it's
the distance from the mean.
So let me call this, say, m, maybe, just to
have a smaller letter. But I could put it.
So it's the distance from the mean minus m.
It's the expected value, the average value
of x minus m squared. And in general,
of course, the expected, this covariance
matrix I could express with that e
notation. But let me just stretch it as far
as, what would be the expected
value of any function of x?
Well, we've got n possible outputs, x1
to xn. We look at f of x1 up to f of xn. We
weight those by the probabilities that they
happen. So this would be, let me make just
a little corner for this, e letter. So this
would be the probability that that is f of
x1 times the value of f at x1. So this is
the contribution from the x1 possibility.
And now we include them all. So it will be
f output f of xn with probability pn. And
if that f of x is x minus m squared, then
we get what we expect. And let me remember
that. So I just want to
keep going with variance.
So it's the sum. It's the first probability
times the first output. Minus the mean
squared.
The last probability times that last
output, xn minus m squared. And everybody
should know a second expression, a second
way to do that sum. If I just write out
those squares and combine them a little
differently, I get a second expression,
which is really useful, often a little
faster to compute. So can I just do that?
So that's x1 squared minus 2 x1 m1 plus m1
squared, right? And then same thing here,
pn times xn squared minus
2 xn m plus m squared.
Good with that?
Plus n. Oh, sorry.
No, I mean, am I?
Oh, it's just an m. Correct. Thank you.
Thank you. Just an m. Good. OK. Can we take
that sum? So I get p1 x1 squared
if I take these, the first guys.
So I've accounted for this and this. Now
I'll take minus 2 p1 x1 m. So p1 x1 m plus
pn
xn m.
I'm just writing it all out, and I'm going
to recombine it. So now I have p1 m squared
plus p2 m squared plus pn m squared. So
what do I have from the p1 m squared all
the way up to pn m squared? Are you with
me? So m squared is in every term. So I'm
going to have an m squared. And what's it
multiplied by? p1 here, p2 here, pn here. I
add those up, and I get? 1. So that's it.
OK. And now I'll just simplify this thing.
So this is really the expected value of
what? What am I seeing in this term?
The expected value
of x squared, right.
Different from the expected value of x
minus m squared, of course. This is just
the first term from here. But now what do
I get for this second term? Well, the point
is that m comes out. So this is minus an
m and a 2. And what do I have left? So I've
used up the m. I've used up the
2. p1 x1 plus pn xn. What's that?
Everybody should just pay attention
to this. Trivial. I mean, we're just doing
high school algebra. We're here. But p1
x1 up to pn xn is m. So I have another m, m
squared there. And I have a plus m squared
from the end. So you see that it is another
expression, the expected value of x squared
minus m squared. Just algebra. But that is
the same as this.
So that if you happen to have a handy way
to compute the expected value of x squared,
you would just subtract m squared,
and you'd have the same as this. Yeah, it's
just algebra. OK. Can I? Let's go a little
deeper with something here, if I can find
it. There are two great inequalities
in statistics. And the first one is due to
Markov. And I don't know if
you know Markov's inequality.
It comes out easily. In fact, too easily.
I'm kind of happy with the discussion. Now
I've jumped to section 5 of the book.
So I'll need to post section 5, which is
probability and statistics. And you'll see
this Markov inequality. So it just involves
this stuff. So that's why I'll go
do it now. Markov's inequality.
He was a great Russian mathematician,
well, probably about 1900. And we will see
Markov chains and Markov processes. That's
beautiful linear algebra. But this little
inequality is not matrices. It's just
playing with these. And it applies to non
-negative events. So I'm going to, when,
shall I say applies when? When all the x,
all the outputs are
greater or equal to 0.
So it's going to be a, it's going to, I'm
going to use that fact. So it doesn't apply
to something like Gaussian. Because they're
Gaussian. The outputs go all the way from
minus infinity to infinity. It does
apply to a lot of important ones.
A simple one. So I'm just saying,
let's suppose, I'll give the proof for this
finite probability. And there would
be a similar proof, similar discussion
everywhere here for continuous probability.
So what does Markov say? Let me be sure I
get it right, because I'm not a pro at
this. It's natural to want to estimate the
probability
that x is greater or equal some number a.
Get some idea. What's the probability of x
being greater or equal a? So what do we
know? This is certainly a number between 0
and 1.
That number is going to get smaller as a
increases, because we're going to be asking
for more. If I take a to be, say, twice the
mean. Yeah, suppose I take a to be twice
the mean. Can I estimate what that
probability could be? And that's what
Markov has done. He says
the probability of that is at least.
At most. Sorry. Let's see. I used to have
an eraser. At least. Sorry. At most. Yes.
Got it? Got it? Is less or equal to the
mean. x bar is another way to write the
mean. Divided by a. And this is the mean
over a. Or it's the expected value of x
over a. We could see
any of those notations.
And as we expect,
as a increases,
the probability, this number goes down. The
probability goes down of exceeding a. So
that's a pretty simple estimate to get this
probability just in terms of the number a,
which has to come in, because it's part
of the question, and the mean, x. So let me
take an example as a equals 3.
So I'm going to try. I'm going to just, for
example, suppose a was 3. I want to show
that the probability of x, x being greater
than or equal to 3. Yeah. OK. So let's. We
don't know. We don't have many facts to
work with. So if we write those down, we
should see the reason. OK. So I know
that the mean is e of x. So let's see. Am I
going to take? Yeah. I'm going to. For
example. Let's take the mean to be 1. So
I'm going to imagine that the mean is 1.
And that I'm asking for what's the chance
that x will be bigger than 3. And I'll get
an estimate of 1 third. So I'm trying to
show that the probability of x greater or
equal 3 is less or equal to the mean. I'm
saying is 1. a is 3. So it's less or equal
1 third. Now, why is that true? That's what
I have to show. OK. I think that if I
write down what I know, I'll see it.
All right. So let me just raise that a
little so that I have room to write. So
what do I know?
I know the definition of the mean. So I
know that x1 times p1 plus x2 p2 plus x3
p3. Allow me to get carried
away here. x5 p5, say, is what?
So what I've written
down there is the mean.
1. So this is the
fact that I know is 1.
And what is it that I want to prove? I want
to know the probability of being greater
or equal 3. So what's the probability
that the result will be greater or equal 3?
It's p3. So this is saying that p3 plus p4.
So these are the probabilities. These are
the different ways that I might be greater
or equal 3. And I'm claiming that that's
less or equal 1 third.
What I liked about this elementary approach
is that I've stated these facts, these
probability assumptions and conclusions.
So I'm not going to go into the details of
the probability assumptions directly in
terms of numbers. So I just want to show
that if this is true, then that's true.
Let's see. I guess I'm thinking that the,
I'm sorry, I even took a more special
case. I'm taking the case where x1 is 1.
x4 is 4. And x5 is 5. So that satisfies my
condition that the outputs 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5
are all Markov only applies when they're
all greater or equal 0. So I had to take a,
so I'm just imagining the special case
where the possible outputs are 1, 2, 3, 4,
5. Their probabilities are p1, p2, p3, p4,
p5. The mean is 1. And what I want to show
is that the probability of being greater
than 3 is less or equal 1 third. And can
you put together these two? Can you
conclude, given this, we want to conclude
that. Let me just step back a
minute. So what do we know here?
We know this, the first line. And we want
to prove the second line. We know one more
thing.
All the probability, well, we know the
probabilities add to 1. And we know they're
all greater or equal 0. So let me put those
facts in here too. We know that p1 plus p2
plus p3 plus p4 plus p5 is 1. That we
know. And we also know that all the p's are
greater than or equal 0. OK. OK.
So here we go. I think my idea is this is
looking at 3 times p3 plus p4 plus p5. So
I'm going to take 3p3
plus 3p4 away from this.
So this will say p1 plus 2p2 plus 3 of
p3. 3 plus p4 plus p5. I'm just picking out
three of those guys. Plus I have one more
p4 to account for. And two more p5 gives 1.
Good?
Now this is what
I'm trying to prove.
So that is here. I'm trying to prove that
this thing is, what am I trying to prove
about that number? Sorry, I'm talking a
lot. But now I've really come to the point.
What is Markov telling me about that
number that is less or equal to? 1. OK. I'm
trying to prove that this is less or
equal 1. That's what Markov tells me.
But suppose it was greater than 1. Do you
see the problem? Do you see why it can't be
greater than 1? Because why?
All the other terms are greater or equal
0. Probabilities are greater or equal 0.
These are all greater or equal 0. And the
total thing adds to 1. So that this piece
has to be less or equal 1. That's it. So
a lot of talking there. Simple idea. And
you'll see exactly this example written
down in the notes. OK. And then you'll see
a more conventional
proof of Markov's inequality
and simple inequality steps. But they're
somehow more mysterious. For me, this was
explicit. So that's Markov. Chebyshev is
the other great Russian probabilist of the
time. And he
gets his inequality.
So there are the two. There's Markov's
inequality. Let me write it down again what
it was. Here was
Markov's inequality.
And Markov's assumption. Chebyshev doesn't
make that assumption. So now no assumption
that the outputs are greater or equal 0. It
doesn't come in. OK. Now what is Chebyshev
trying to estimate? OK. Let's move
to Chebyshev. And that's the last guy.
So Chebyshev is
interested in the probability
that x minus the mean,
m, can I use that for mean,
is probably greater or equal
to a, the probability of being sort of a
distance a away from the mean. So again, as
a increases, I'm asking more. I'm asking it
to be further away from the mean. And the
probability will drop. And then the
question is, can we estimate this? So this
is a different estimate, but it's a similar
question. And what's Chebyshev's answer
for this? So this is the probability of
this. I have to put a big. That's all one
mouthful. The
probability of being.
That this x minus m is greater or equal to
a. And again, we're going to have is less
or equal to
sigma squared now
comes in over a squared.
So that's Chebyshev. And I just take time
today to do these two, because they involve
analysis. They're basic tools. It's sort
of the first thing you think of if you're
trying to estimate a probability. Does it
fit Markov? And Markov only applies. So
I'll put only applies when the x's are all
greater or equal to 0. Here, does it fit
Chebyshev? And now we're taking absolute
values. So we're not concerned about the
size of x. And we're taking the distance
from m. So we're obviously in the world of
variances. We're distances from m. OK. And
the proof of Chebyshev comes directly from
Markov. So I'm going to apply Markov.
So good thing that Markov came first.
To, now let me
just say this right,
to a new, let me call it y.
This will be a new output.
And it will
be x minus m squared.
So that's, of course, with the same
probability. So yi is xi minus m, the mean,
squared. And the same
probability, same probabilities, pi.
So I guess if I'm going to apply, I'm
just going to take that, take the y's here
instead of the x's here.
And then apply Markov. So what is x bar?
So if I want to apply Markov, I have to
figure out the mean of x. Over here, I
have to figure out the mean of y. What is
the mean of y? The mean value,
the sum of probabilities times y's.
You're supposed to recognize
it. This is the sum of probabilities.
And my y's are the xi
minus the mean squared.
So this is the mean for this y thing that
I've brought in. Has that formula. And we
recognize what that quantity is. That is,
that's sigma squared. Sigma squared for the
original x's. So that's just, that's great.
So the mean is sigma, is the old sigma
squared. Those are exclamation marks. OK,
so then I, do you see that now Markov is
looking like, or Chebyshev is looking like
Markov? Because here, over here will be
the, now I want the expected value of y
over the, let's see. Yeah. So the expected
y is going to be that. And now what
do I have to divide by? I want to know
probabilities of something being bigger,
of this thing being bigger than a. But now
I'm looking at the y's. So the probability
of, if x minus m is greater than or equal
to a, then x minus xi minus m squared is
greater or equal a squared. So my a over
here for x is now turning in this problem,
where I'm looking at probability greater or
equal a, but squaring it, this
is the a squared.
So that's Markov applied to y. Here is
Markov applied to x. And x had to be
greater or equal 0. So over here, Chebyshev
took a y, which was greater or equal 0,
then just applied Markov, and recognized
that what, that the mean was of his
variable, x minus m squared, was exactly
sigma squared. And it fell out. So again,
here is a very simple proof for Markov.
And then everybody agrees that Chebyshev
follows right away from Markov. OK, so
those are two basic inequalities. Now, the
other topic that I wanted to deal with was
covariance, covariance matrix. You have to
get comfortable. What is
that? What's the covariance?
OK. So covariance.
Covariance matrix.
And it will be m by m when I
have m, m, sorry, experiments, m
at once. Now, let me take m equal to 2.
You'll see everything for m equal to 2. So
it's a, we're expecting
to get a 2 by 2 matrix.
What are we starting with? We're doing
two experiments at once. So we have two
outputs, two outputs,
an x and a y.
So the x's are the outputs from the x
experiment. The y's are the output from a
second experiment. We're flipping
two coins. So let's take that example, two
coins.
Coin 1
gets 0 or 1 with p equal
to probability 1 half. Coin 2,
0 or 1 with probability 1
half. So they're fair coins.
But what I haven't said is,
is there a connection between the output?
This is the x. This is the y. If I glue the
coins together, then the two outputs are
the same. I think for me, this is a model
question that brings out
the main point of covariance.
Separately,
quite independently, then there is no,
I can't, I don't know more about y from
knowing x. If I know the answer to one
flip, it doesn't tell me anything about the
second if they're independent.
Uncorrelated. But if the two coins are
glued together, then heads will come up for
both coins. It'll be, I'll only have two
possibilities. That'll be heads, heads or
tails, tails. Let me write down those
two different scenarios. So unglued,
I never expected to write that
word in the math class. Unglued.
And what am I going to write
down? I'm going to write down
a matrix. With heads, tails for coin 1.
And heads and tails for coin 2. So the
possibilities are coin 1 gets heads and
coin 2 gets heads. What's the probability
of that? This is the unglued case. So I'm
going to create a little probability matrix
of joint probabilities. That's really the
key word that I'm discussing here. Joint
probabilities.
So let's complete that matrix.
So I have unglued coins, independent coins.
I flip them both. What are the chances of
getting heads on both? 1 fourth.
What are the chances of, what do I put
in here? This means heads on the first coin
and tails on the second coin. And the
probability of that is? 1 fourth. And 1
fourth here and 1 fourth here. So I have
the four possibilities, which I put into a
2 by 2 matrix instead of a long vector. My
four possibilities are heads, heads, heads,
tails, tails, heads, and tails, tails. And
they have equal probability 1 fourth. But
now if they're glued,
heads and tails on the first coin, heads
and tails on the second, on the first coin,
heads and tails on the second coin. OK. Now
what do I put in there? So the two coins
are glued together. What is the
chance that they both come up heads?
1 half. Right. 1 half. Because if one comes
up heads, the other one is glued to it. It
will also. What's the probability of heads,
tails? Heads on one, tails on the other
is, of course, 0. Thanks. And here, 0.
And here, 1 half. So what I've created are
those two different setups, two different
scenarios of unglued and glued. And in this
one, we have, but each experimental setup
has its matrix of joint probabilities.
That's the thing, that there are four
numbers here, four numbers. We have all
possibilities. We have any possible x
and, at the same time, any possible y. So
suppose we were running
three experiments, and we had,
well, so what would be the situation if I
was running three experiments with three
independent fair coins? So I'd be in this
unglued picture, but I would have three
different experiments that I'm running.
Then what would I be looking at then? Just
the whole idea is to see what is this joint
probability. So suppose I have three coins
unglued.
Then I want to know the probability of
getting heads on the first, heads on the
second, heads on the third will
be what? Just give me that number.
Probability that all three of them
independently come up heads? 1 eighth. OK.
But now my question is, so what do I
have? Then I have probability of heads, say
tails, heads, heads. I've got three indices
here, eventually down to probability of
tails, tails, tails. Everybody sees that
the numbers are going to be 1 eighth.
So where do those fit in?
They don't fit in a matrix, because I've
got three indices here. So I guess what
we're seeing, I sort of realized today,
we're seeing for the first time a tensor. A
tensor is a three
-way structure,
three -way matrix, you
could say. So we have,
I guess I think of this instead of a square
like that, an ordinary matrix. I have to
think of a cube, right? I have a cube with
two rows, two columns, and two whatevers.
Layers, somebody might say layers for that.
Do you see that the matrix has become a
three -way thing, a tensor? And the entries
in that tensor, so it's 2 by 2 by 2.
Instead of m by n for a matrix, I have to
give you the number of rows, the number of
columns, and the number of layers going
into the board. So rows going one way,
columns, rows, and then layers are going
in deep. So it will have eight entries.
And of course, in this simple case,
each will be 1 8 in that unglued, totally
independent way. But then you can imagine
some dependence. So what would happen if I
glued coins 1 and 3?
I would still have a tensor, still have a 2
by 2 by 2 tensor of all the possibilities.
Now, but some of those are going to have
probability 0, the joint probability. If
I've glued coin 1 to coin 3, then the
probability of jointly seeing heads on 1,
whatever on 2, tails on 3 will be 0, right?
Because that can't happen if I've glued
coins 1 and 3. So I'll
have eight entries in here.
The unglued case.
And then I could have a case
where two coins are glued.
And as I say, I think I would have
one quarter four times, probably.
So what will be the situation
for three coins glued?
What will be the entries in the matrix of
joint probabilities? What will be the joint
probability? So the probability of heads,
heads, heads, of seeing heads from all
three will be 1 half. 1 half, because
I'm flipping this heavy mix of three coins
together.
1 half, twice.
Actually, this is a good introduction to
tensors in a way. Because the first step in
understanding tensors is to think of three
-way matrices. Think of three -way things.
We just haven't done that. And now we have
to do it. And of course, four -way or n
-way tensors are now understood. So
these are tensors with very special, simple
things. So now I have to say, what is the
covariance matrix? What's the covariance
matrix? So now I'm ready for that. And I'll
put it here. That's the final topic for
today.
So the covariance matrix.
So I'm saying matrix, because I'm just
going to have, yeah, the covariance matrix.
Yeah, it's going to be 2 by 2, or for two
coins. So it is a matrix. For three coins,
it will be 3 by 3. But it is a matrix. OK.
So how is it defined? And what am I going
to call it? I think I'll call it v,
because really the key idea is variance.
Covariance is telling us that we're also
interested in the joint outcome, an x and a
y. OK. So it's a variance. So I'm
going to add up over all possible i and j.
Over all, sorry, all possible
outcomes. Yeah, that's right.
The guy in our 2 by 2 matrix, like that
one or that one, depending on the gluing or
not gluing. So pij, this is, let me say
what it is. This is the probability that x
is xi, and that the second
output, that this is yj.
And let me give you a second. An example
to keep in mind. Suppose I'm looking at age
and height. So suppose x is the age of the
sample, the person, and y is the height.
Then
I want to know, so what fraction have
a certain age and a certain height? It's
every, I'm looking at every pair, age
and height. Age 11, height 4 feet. Age 12,
height 5 feet. Age 11, height 4, 5 feet.
Each combination. So pij is the probability
that these will both happen.
So what could, just, I'm going to add more
to it here. But that joint probability is
really important. So I'm going to ask you
more about that. Suppose that I take these
pij's and that I add up p1j plus p2j plus
p3j. In other words, I sum the pij's over
i. So I'm looking at a rho, rho i of my
matrix. So what, just, so let me ask the
question. If I, maybe I have
to put it somewhere else.
What is, what means,
what's the meaning of the sum of pij over
the i's? What does that quantity look like?
So that's a probability. pij is the
probability of getting a certain i and a
certain j. But now I'm including all the
i's. So what am I seeing there? pj. Thanks.
pj. This is pj.
That's the probability of seeing j in the
second guy. Because I had to see something.
If I see j in the second one, I'm allowed
to see anything here in the first one. But
I'm adding those all up. So that's the
point. Those would be called the marginals.
In my matrices, I would be adding up along
a row or adding up down a column. Those are
called the marginals of
the joint probabilities. So the marginals
would be the individual probabilities, pi
and pj, in the case of two experiments
going on at the same time. Yeah. It's just
like new ideas. Everything today has
been sort of straightforward, but it's
different. OK. Now I'm going to complete
the, the definition of this covariance
matrix. So it's going to be,
I want to have a square.
So it's going to be, and it should be, this
is putting x and the mean of x. Mean 1, I
could call it, or
mean of x. And y,
the distance from the mean of y, times, so
it's going to be column times row. Same x
minus the mean of x.
y minus the mean of y.
xi,
yj.
So
can you look at this formula? Two
experiments. Two experiments. Two coins.
Two experiments.
I get a 2 by 2 matrix. Everybody sees that.
A column times a row, 2 by 2 matrix. And
let's just see what would be the 1, 1 entry
in that matrix. This is the covariance
matrix. So what is the
1, 1 entry in that matrix?
That times that, which is that thing
squared, times all the pijs. Add them up.
What do you think I get for that? I get the
variance of the x experiment. The standard
variance of the x experiment. So v, I have
to tell you what v is now here. v, this is
v. 2 by 2 matrix. I get the variance of the
x experiment. What do I get down here? The
variance of the y experiment by itself,
because it's y's times y's that give me the
2, 2 entry. So this is just sigma y
squared. Sigma y squared. OK, but the
novelty is the 1, 2, and it'll be
symmetric. So it's a symmetric matrix. So
this is v transpose. I just have to see
here. So I have pij times the distance of
this guy times this guy. That's what's
going to show up in the 1, 2 position.
It'll be in row 1. It'll be in column 2.
It's the x. It's the distances. So what
will it be in the case of unglued
coins, independent coins? Zero.
I mean, I'm just feeling like 0. I haven't
done the computation. But I know that when
I have independent experiments, then this
covariance, which everybody would write as
sigma xy, and it's the same here. It's
symmetric. Sigma yx, if you like. So those
subscripts are telling me that the sum
of the p's, joint probabilities, times the
distance of x from its mean, the distance
of y from its mean, added up over all the
possibilities. So the case of unglued
coins, the case of independent ones, in
that case, those are 0. Maybe worth just
writing that out. You would get 0. So you
have a diagonal matrix. The diagonal matrix
is just the separate variances, because
that's all. You do independent. Experiments
are independent. So all you can really
expect information is sigma x squared and
sigma y squared. But if the two coins are
glued together,
then what? If the two coins are glued
together, well, let me just say, because
time is up, this matrix will be singular.
If the two coins were glued together, this
would be, the determinant would be 0 here.
The sigma xy in the glued case would be
squared, would be the same as
sigma x squared sigma y squared.
Actually, we're probably getting all these
1 quarters, and that would make sense. So
the case of a, so I'll just end with
this statement. This matrix is positive
semidefinite always. Positive semidefinite
always, because it's column times row. We
know that's positive semidefinite. And it's
multiplied by numbers greater or equal 0.
So it's a combination of rank 1 positive
semidefinite. So it's positive semidefinite
or positive definite. It's certainly
positive definite in the independent case
when it's diagonal. And the totally
dependent case, when the coins are
completely stuck together, that will be the
semidefinite case when these entries would
all be the same, actually. So that's
a first look at covariance matrices. It
brought in tensors. It brought in joint
probabilities. It brought in column times
row. It kept symmetry. And we recognized
positive definite or positive semidefinite.
So in between, coins that were
partly glued, partly independent but not
completely independent experiments,
then this number would be smaller. The
determinant would be, this wouldn't be 0,
but it would be smaller than these numbers.
OK, we're, I've run four minutes
over. You're very kind to say. So have a
wonderful break. And I'll see you a
week from Monday. Good. Thanks.